Martha Voegeli Papers, 1946-1965
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Martha Voegeli papers
1946-65
Voegeli, Martha
MS 168
1 box (.5 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Birth control advocate; pacifist; animal welfare advocate; and physician. The Martha Voegeli papers include correspondence and writings. Correspondence includes Voegeli's letters to medical professionals and government officials espousing her views on birth control, famine in India, world peace, race relations, and animal welfare. Replies from Dr. Clarence Gamble, Aldous Huxley, Dorothy Brush, LeRoy Collins, Dr. Mary Calderone, Albert Schweitzer, Dr. Harrison Brown, and Arnold Toynbee are included. Of particular interest are her writings and correspondence about male sterilization through the thermic method, selective breeding, and her "One-Meal-A-Day-For-People-Over-Forty" solution to famine in India.
Martha Voegeli was born in Switzerland. She received her M.A. from Columbia University and her M.D. from the University of Berlin and the University of Paris. Voegeli owned a private hospital in India, where she specialized in surgery. She retired to Switzerland in 1950.
The Martha Voegeli papers include correspondence and writings. Most of the correspondence consists of copies of Voegeli's letters to medical professionals and government officials espousing her views on birth control, famine in India, world peace, race relations, and animal rights. There are a few replies, including those from Dr. Clarence Gamble, Aldous Huxley, Dorothy Brush, LeRoy Collins, Dr. Mary Calderone, Albert Schweitzer, Dr. Harrison Brown, and Arnold Toynbee. There are also two speeches by LeRoy Collins (Governor of Florida) on race relations, 1958. Of particular interest are her writings and correspondence about male sterilization through the thermic method (1952-55), selective breeding (1946-47), and her "One-Meal-A-Day-For-People-Over-Forty" solution to famine in India (1946).
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
History of the Collection
Martha Voegeli donated her papers to the Sophia Smith Collection from 1960 to 1967.
Search Terms
Brush, Dorothy Hamilton--Correspondence; Collins, LeRoy; Gamble, Clarence James, 1894- --Correspondence; Huxley, Aldous, 1894-1963--Correspondence; Toynbee, Arnold, 1852-1883--Correspondence; Voegeli, Martha; Animal welfare--History--Sources; Sterilization (birth control)--History--Sources; Women physicians--History--20th century--Sources
- Brown, Dr. Harrison (California Institute of Technology) to Dr Voegeli, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Collins, LeRoy (Governor of Florida) to M. Voegeli; and two speeches by Governor Collins on race relations, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Gamble, Dr. Clarence, 1953-54 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Humane Society of the United States, 1963-65 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Huxley, Aldous (on religion and science), 1961 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Price, Alice (Mrs. T. Glen), 1953 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Pyke, David, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Toynbee, Arnold, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Belgian Society for Sexual Advice, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Brown, Dr. Harrison, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Brush, Dorothy (Editor of IPPF News), 1956 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Gamble, Dr. Clarence, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Nelson, Dr. Warren, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Planned Parenthood Federation of America, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Price, Alice, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Pyke, Dr. David, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Lambarene, Albert Schweitzer, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- "Education and World Peace": typescript, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
- "World Organization for Thinkers and Saints": typescript, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Articles on population problems (by others), 1954-55 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Catholic Institute for Social Research, Geneva, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Famine (in India) One-Meal-A-Day-For-People-Over-Forty (by Voegeli); and correspondence to Sir Norman Strathie and Eleanor Roosevelt, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- General Electric vs. AT&T (on submitted ideas), 1956-58 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Male sterilization
  - Selective breeding: correspondence and writings, 1946-47 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Thermic method
    - Articles and correspondence, 1952-56 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Correspondence with government of India, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Correspondence to world leaders, 1953-55 (Box 1, Folder 27)